All right. Today's דף daf *daf*, as was said, is ס"ה *Samech-He*,
but we start on ס"ד עמוד ב' *Samech-Dalet Amud Bet* on the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*,
and let's take a look. Very fascinating דף daf *daf* today. מצות
העומר להביא מן הקרוב *Mitzvat ha-omer lehavi min ha-karov*. If the מצוה
*mitzvah* is to bring from the grain that is near ירושלים Yerushalayim
*Yerushalayim*. לא ביכר הקרוב בירושלים *Lo biker ha-karov bi-Yerushalayim*, if the grain
near ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* was not yet ripe, מביאין אותו מכל מקום
*mevi'in oto mikol makom*, you bring it from everywhere. Everywhere is of
course limited for everywhere in Israel. The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* said earlier
in an explicit משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* that the עומר Omer *omer* can
only come from grain from Israel, but ideally from grain closer to
ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. Did the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* have
its own fields? They took it from? No. No. מעשה שבא העומר
מגגות צריפין *Ma'aseh she-ba ha-omer migagot srifin*. There was a time the
עומר omer *omer* had to come from a place called גגות צריפין
Gagot Tserifin *Gagot Srifin*, the roofs of צריפין *srifin*, which are like
teepees. But anyway, that was the name of a village or something.
ושתי הלחם מבקעת עין סוחר *Ve-shte halachem mi-bik'at Ein Socher*, and the
type that they only had ripe wheat grain in a place called
עין סוחר *Ein Socher* when it was time for the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem *shte halachem*. Okay. מר מאי טעמא *Mar mai ta'ama*? What's
the reason that you're supposed to bring from the nearby grain? אי
בעית אימא משום כרמל *Iy ba'it eima mishum karmel*.
Because we do a דרש *d'rash* on כרמל *karmel*, because it says
you bring the עומר omer, *omer* from כרמל *karmel*, which is we
read it as רך ומלא *rach ve-malei*, that the grain has to
be full and soft. So the closer you bring it to ירושלים
Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, the softer, you know, the riper, not riper, fresher the
grain is. It doesn't get hard yet. Precisely. כר *Kar* means... no,
they play... כר *kar* is רך *rach* and מלא *malei*. Soft. So
כר *kar* is רך *rach* and מלא *malei*, like full and ripe
and soft, so not, you know, fresh. ואי בעית אימא *Ve-iy ba'it
eima*, and if you want, משום דאין מעבירין על המצות *mishum de-ein
ma'avirin al hamitzvot*. You don't pass over the מצות *mitzvot* if you
have the grain that's right here, but pass by it and go
somewhere else, משום דאין מעבירין על המצות *mishum de-ein ma'avirin al hamitzvot*.
Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has a whole discussion, there's whole סוגיות *sugyot*
about what constitutes מעבירין על המצות *ma'avirin al hamitzvot*. You know, classic
example for example about מעבירין על המצות *ma'avirin al hamitzvot* and אין
מעבירין *ein ma'avirin*, important would be we learned before, you know, earlier
in מנחות *Menachot* that you put on your תפילין של יד *tefillin
shel yad* before your תפילין של ראש Rosh *tefillin shel rosh*. What
happens if you stick your hand in your תפילין *tefillin* bag and
you take out by accident your תפילין של ראש Rosh *tefillin shel
rosh*? Okay, now there, אין מעבירין על המצות שתצא *ein ma'avirin al
hamitzvot she-teze* that you should put on your תפילין של ראש *tefillin
shel rosh* first. You shouldn't put it aside and get your תפילין
של יד *tefillin shel yad*. However, there you actually do for the
sake of the importance of having the יד *yad* on first, actually
do pass over it and switch the order. But that's where those
two things come in conflict. The idea that you encountered this מצוה
*mitzvah*, do you put it aside in order to do another one?
That's the principle of אין מעבירין על המצות *ein ma'avirin al hamitzvot*.
It's a little strange here because here you are not not doing
one מצוה *mitzvah* for the sake of another, you are trying to
do one מצוה *mitzvah* ideally. Now you could still say that you
have an opportunity to use this grain, you don't set aside this
grain to say, well, I'll find some other better grain somewhere else.
But you know, it's not always that simple. Like if you imagine,
let's say a mile to the east of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* is
ripe grain, but ten miles to the west of it is also
ripe grain that's better quality. If I leave ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* and
I go to the west, I'm not exactly מעביר על מצות *ma'avir
al mitzvot* because there's closer grain to the east, right? So the
idea that it's not even if you encounter it and you set
it aside, but that you're sort of able to say, well, this
is the closer one, the more available one, even though I haven't
yet encountered it, and therefore I should go this way rather than
the other way. It's interesting that that's included in this idea of
אין מעבירין על המצות *ein ma'avirin al hamitzvot*. It seems to be.
Right. I mean you're right, I drew the scenario that you didn't
have to encounter it yet. Okay, but that does... it does seem
that it includes even that case.
Right. I mean, you're right. I thought you were saying all things
being equal you go closer to ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, but you're saying
is even if all things are not equal?
Oh,
I think the סתם דמשנה *stam de-Mishnah* is that as long as
it's ripe and it satisfies the ripe criteria, of course you make
a... you're right. Sometimes you do pass something over just because... exactly.
You שחט *shechted* an animal on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* for a קרבן
korban. *korban* and there's a nicer one here. We're going to ignore
this to do the nicer one. It's an excellent point. You're right.
I was somehow
assuming that the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* meant even all things not being
equal. If it is all things being equal, then of course it
makes total sense. Okay, yes.
You know, I always was curious about this with regard to תפילין
*tefillin* and other things, other principles like that. I mean these sound
to me like principles that are certainly not בדיעבד *bedi'avad*.
Right. Well,
nobody is saying that this is בדיעבד *bedi'avad* here, too. Right. Nobody
is saying that if you brought from far away, you know, that
you're not יוצא *yotze*. It says מצות העומר להביא מן הקרוב *mitzvat
ha-omer lehavi min ha-karov*, right? לא הביא מן ה *lo hevi min
ha*... you know, then it says לא ביכר *lo biker*. You're right.
It could have said the bigger חידוש *chiddush* of the משנה mishnah.
*Mishnah* was even ביכר *biker*, if for some reason you went from
far away, you're still יוצא *yotze*. But that's the assumption. You're right.
This is all בגדר מצוה *be-geder mitzvah*, not עכובה *eikuva*.
But what is the... the literal meaning of כרמל *karmel*?
I'd have to look at an English translation. I don't know, actually.
I think some... I don't know.
What... what does your English say? Have anything?
Oh, I do.
You'll tell us. All right, let's start with a very, very quick
question. Yes. Did they go to somebody's private field or did they
go to like a public? Private
field, it seems.
It's a lot easier not to have your own thing, wait until
you find somebody who has good grain and then you get the,
you know what I'm saying? Better than having to tend the whole
field and then maybe it's not going to produce. Plump. Well that's
certainly, okay plump is certainly a good word. It's certainly the sense
in which the גמרא Gemara is reading it, whether that is... you
can't trust Artscroll to give you like the, you know, פשט. pshat.
They're reading it through the lens of the גמרא. Gemara But anyway.
All right, let's go on. Somebody can look at, you know, look
at a different translation. Now, מעשה שבא אומרים הגיעה מגגות צריפין פעם
אחת. Maaseh sheba omrim higiat meGagot Tserifin paam achat. The עומר omer,
came from this place called גגות צריפין once. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Now we're going to find out the story about how it came
there. תנו רבנן כששרו מלכי בית חשמונאי זה על זה. Tanu Rabbanan
keshesharu malchei beit Chashmonai ze al ze.
When the kings of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim were laying siege one to
the other, והורקנוס מבחוץ ואריסטובולוס מבפנים. veHorkanous mibachutz veAristobolus mibifnim. הורקנוס Horkanous
was outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim laying siege to ירושלים Yerushalayim, and אריסטובולוס
Aristobolus was in ירושלים. Yerushalayim, These actually were descendants of the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim and they were yes, and they were fighting against each other
about who gets to be the king, and you know, different ones
of them at different stages were enlisting the aid of the... of
the Romans or, no, it was before the Romans, excuse me, of
the Seleucids. Anyway,
it's actually in the גמרא's Gemara description, they were two brothers. The
גמרא's Gemara, actual description is quite accurate because it says when they
were צרים זה על זה דהיה tzarim ze al ze dehayah because
if you read Josephus, which of course I do every night, but
I know I did in preparation for this שיעור, shiur, it actually
it reversed itself. First it used to be that
הורקנוס Horkanous was on the inside and אריסטובולוס Aristobolus was on the
outside and אריסטובולוס Aristobolus conquered ירושלים Yerushalayim and he became king and
then it reversed and now we have our scenario which is that
אריסטובולוס Aristobolus is on the inside and הורקנוס Horkanous is on the
outside. So the גמרא's Gemara phrasing if you pay attention to it
is very appropriate that it sounds like it was going back and
forth. They were צרים זה על זה tzarim ze al ze and
in this moment this is the way it was in this moment
that... well no, not a dialogue like a vacillating war. So at
this moment, I mean it wasn't all in the one time, it
wasn't all one war. One first won and then the other sort
of regrouped and gained troops and new alliances, whatever. Anyway, at this
time הורקנוס Horkanous was on the outside and אריסטובולוס Aristobolus was on
the inside. Okay. בכל יום ויום היו משלשלים להן דינרי בקופה. Bekhol
yom veyom hayu meshalshelim lahen dinarei bekupa. Every day they would lower
down דינרי dinarei in a basket from the walls of ירושלים ומעלין
להן תמידים vemaalin lahen temidim
and the troops on the outside even though they were laying siege
were nice enough to be sending up lambs to use as תמידים
temidim because they presumably at least were, you know, it's one thing
who gets to be king, it's another thing the temple, that's our
central, you know, place of worship, we at least acknowledge that so
they would send up תמידים. temidim.
Okay. היה שם זקן אחד, Hayah sham zaken echad, there was a
certain elderly...
must've been at least 40 days in advance, right?
What? That's a good question. שהיה מכיר בחכמת יוונית. shehayah makir bechokhmat
Yevanit. He knew the
חכמת יוונית, chokhmat Yevanit, the Greek wisdom. From the context it is
clear, I'll talk in a minute what the... how this compares to
the use in another גמרא, Gemara but from the context it's clear
that it means that it was some way that allowed him to
communicate with others without being detected.
Maybe it literally means the Greek language, maybe it means תוספות Tosafot
says that it was maybe certain types of signals, you know, or
Morse code type of thing. Anyway, some form of communication, the Greek
wisdom.
לעז להם בחכמת יוונית. Laaz lahem bechokhmat Yevanit. He spoke to them,
but again the whole word לעז laaz is almost like speaking in
a vernacular. He communicated to them, this was a guy on the
inside of ירושלים, he was basically a traitor and he was communicating
to the people on the outside and the way he did it
without being discovered was using חכמת יוונית, chokhma Yevanit, again whatever exactly
that is, so he communicated to them in this form of Greek
wisdom. ואמר להם, Veamar lahem, he said to the people on the
outside, כל זמן שעסוקין בעבודה אין נמסרין בידכם. kol zman she'asukin baavodah
ein nimisarin beyadkhem.
While the people, while they are still, you know, doing the עבודה
avodah properly, worshipping in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash that will protect
them, they will not be handed over to you. The whole idea
is quite strange because it's not like a particular piece of secret
information that he had that you had to be on the inside
to hand over to people on the outside, right? I mean if
it's a religious belief that if you're worshipping in the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash God is going to protect you, you know, a little
while ago the troops on the outside were on the inside and
they were the ones in possession of ירושלים, so it's a little
strange the way it's being set up like he's secretly passing on
this little bit of information.
Just a morale thing.
Oh, I, oh that's interesting. It's not metaphysical. He's saying, you know,
that their morale depends on them. That's a nice פשט. pshat. I
don't know if it sits with the larger theme here, which is...
but let's take a look, that's a nice פשט. pshat. Okay. למחר,
Lemakhar, so the next day שלשלו להן דינרי בקופה, shilshalu lahen dinarei
bekupa, they lowered down דינרי dinarei in the basket. והעלו להן חזיר.
Vehe'elu lahen chazir. And instead of putting a lamb in it they
put a pig in it. כיון שהגיע לחצי חומה, Keivan shehigia lechatsi
homah, when the pig got halfway up the wall, נעץ צפורניו בחומה,
naatz tzipornav behomah, he, you know, he put his talons... not his
talons, whatever, his nails into the wall, ונזדעזעה ארץ ישראל ארבע מאות
פרסה. venizdaze'ah Eretz Yisrael arba meot parsa. 400 פרסה parsa by 400
פרסה parsa
and the whole land of Israel shook 400 parsangs by 400 parsangs,
which is, you know, that's just a measurement the גמרא Gemara gives
for the size of the land of Israel, not exactly accurate but
whatever. The entire land of Israel shook. One minute, let's finish the
story. Okay, באותה שעה אמרו be'ota sha'ah amru at that moment they
said, ארור שיגדל חזיר arur sheyigadel chazir cursed be the person that
raises pigs, וארור שילמד בנו חכמת יוונית ve'arur sheyelamed beno chochmat yevanit
and cursed be the person that teaches his son the Greek wisdom.
Yeah, I'll talk about that in a minute. דעל אותה שעה שנינו.
de'al ota sha'ah shanu. So now, how is this at all relevant?
Because it was during regarding that time when they were besieged and
they were in ירושלים and they needed to get the stuff for
the, you know, for the קרבנות korbanot from the outside, so we
have a tradition that it was during that time that they could
not get the grain from nearby. Now of course it still means
you need some help from people on the outside to get the
grain. But anyway the way רש״י Rashi explains it is what you
do when you're laying siege to a city is you burn all
of the, you know, all the fields nearby, scorched earth, so that
they don't have where to draw, you know, sustenance from.
So presumably though they were still getting the assistance of the troops
on the outside for קרבנות, korbanot, so it was regarding that time
that we taught, מעשה שבא עומר מגגות צריפים, ma'aseh sheba omer migigot
tsrifim, that's when the עומר omer came from גגות צריפים, Gigot Tsrifim,
ושתי הלחם מבקעת עין סוכר veshtei halechem mibikat ein socher and the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem came from this place of בקעת עין סוכר.
Bikat Ein Socher. Now maybe it could also be by the way,
that maybe it was after they conquered ירושלים,
these troops, then they needed to bring these, you know, the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem and the עומר, omer but they'd already burned the
nearby fields. That makes it a little bit more understandable that then
you don't have to rely on the troops on the outside to
bring the שתי הלחם shtei halechem, and the עומר, omer, which isn't
part of the story, so maybe it was after it was conquered.
Okay and then now here's another interesting, the story's not done because
there's a nice little parallel coming up, you know, before it was
about this old person telling them with חכמת יוונית, chochmat yevanit, so
let's sort of finish this story here and then we can go
back and analyze it. What people are writing stuff here.
This is where the עומר omer comes from because they had
to, you're saying the audio is Donald Duck? I can't take anything
about it. What? Now it was during this time that we have
a tradition in the משנה mishnah when the tradition said once they
had to bring this עומר omer, from this far away place גגות
צריפים, Gigot Tsrifim, we have a tradition that it occurred during this
time when all the nearby fields were scorched. Okay, so now let's
see the end of this story. Okay, כי מטא עומר ki mata
omer when the when
they brought when it was time to bring the עומר, omer לא
הוו ידעי מהיכא אייתי lo havu yadi meheika ayiti they didn't know
where to bring it from because all those nearby fields were scorched,
מהיכא אייתי עומר meheika ayiti omer where to bring it from? אכרזו
achrezu they made an announcement, if anybody knows where there'd be a
good place to get some wheat or excuse me barley for the
עומר omer please let us know. Okay, אתא ההוא חרשא ata hahu
charesha a certain mute came, actually חרש cheresh often means deaf-mute but
here the emphasis is that he's mute. Hopefully it couldn't have been
too deaf because he heard the announcement, maybe somebody told him. Anyway,
אותיב חדא ידיה אאיגרא oteiv chada yadei a-igra he put one hand
on a roof of some building, וחדא ידיה אצריפא vechada yadei a-tsrifa
and one hand on the צריפא tsrifa which looks like a tipi
type of structure/a tent. So he did like this, אמר להו amar
lehu so he said to them,
מרדכי, Mordechai, רש״י Rashi says it's the original מרדכי, Mordechai, תוספות Tosafot
says no that would make him a little you know a little
old. Right, but anyways but somebody by the name of מרדכי, Mordechai,
it doesn't matter, the גמרא Gemara is going to identify him to
the original מרדכי Mordechai anyway in terms of somebody that you know
is very wise and informs you know and is a leader. Anyway,
so מרדכי Mordechai said to the other sort of leaders around there
or or whoever it was that was trying to get the עומר,
omer? מי איכא דוכתא דשמה גגות צריפים וצריפים גגות, mi ika duchta
desh'ma Gigot Tsrifim u-Tsrifim Gigot, he said oh so does anybody know
is there a place called גגות צריפים Gigot Tsrifim or צריפים גגות?
Tsrifim Gigot? Because he's putting one hand on a roof and one
hand on a צריף. tsrif. So then they said oh yeah, תאקא,
taka, בדקו ואשכחו badku ve-ashkechu
they found yeah there was a place called גגות צריפים Gigot Tsrifim
and therefore they sent and they got the wheat from there. Now
כי בעא לאתויי שתי הלחם ki ba le-aytuyei shtei halechem when it
was time to bring the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, לא הוו ידעי
מהיכא לאתויי lo havu yadi meheika le-aytuyei
they didn't know where to bring it from, where is there a
place where there's ripe wheat? All the wheat nearby is not available,
is burned, destroyed. אכרזו achrezu they made an announcement, אתא גברא חרשא
ata gavra charesha again this deaf-mute but really this mute person came.
אותיב ידיה אעיניה oteiv yadei a-einei he put one hand on his
eyes, right, וחדא ידיה אסיכרא vechada yadei a-sichra and one hand on
a סיכרא sichra which רש״י Rashi says is basically a hole through
which a door bolt goes, that's called a סוכר. socher.
So remember the place they brought it from was called עין סוכר.
Ein Socher. So anyway אמר להו מרדכי amar lehu Mordechai so מרדכי
Mordechai said to the people around there,
ומי איכא דוכתא דשמה עין סוכר u-mi ika duchta desh'ma Ein Socher
hey is there any place called עין סוכר Ein Socher or סוכר
עין socher ayin or maybe סוכר עין? socher ayin? בדקו ואשכחו. badku
ve-ashkechu. Okay and they found תאקא taka there was this place called
עין סוכר Ein Socher so that's how they brought it from there.
Now there was a certain nice symmetry and parallel that there was
a like old person using secret language to communicate how to get
in and how to sort of do the wrong thing, send the
pig which led to them
you know winning but
ultimately you know doing something terrible. They can now actually bring what
they need to bring. So other than noting that parallel I'm not
sure here about any sort of larger message, but it is interesting
that almost they reversed what they did to get into ירושלים, at
least now they're trying to do the positive and they're using these
types of or some other type of signal in order to do
that.
What do you think about the חזיר chazir and the...
yeah, I do want to say about the חזיר chazir something, I
wanted to say a few quick things about the חזיר chazir and
the Greek wisdom. I actually made some copies of this, excuse me.
Wait,
let me just finish this one. Okay, so first of all about
the חזיר. chazir. First of all, I do wonder, you know, it
speaks about the חזיר chazir putting its nails into the
wall. חז"ל Chazal often point out that חזיר chazir is the only
non-kosher animal that has split hooves and
but does not chew its cud. And often it says like the
חזיר chazir tries to deceive, it shows its toes to say, look,
I'm כשר, kosher, I'm כשר. kosher. So I do wonder again if
the idea of cleaving its nails in is somehow some type of
a sense about somebody who appears to be כשר kosher trying to
get in and you know maybe is that the whole message here
about these two brothers and their fighting and it's all like this
is not how we imagine what a real Jewish kingship is supposed
to be about, it's obviously all political and nobody's really being too
פרום frum about anything and so is there some sense of like
appearing to be כשר kosher and trying to get into ירושלים and
control and so on. That's just one thing. Now, another thing I
will say is, another thing I will say is that in Josephus,
I don't have time to read it all, I'll pass this out,
put it up on the blog. Anyway, in Josephus Antiquities 14:2, again,
which I read every night, anyway they have the story about this
whole thing. And in this story it's not about the חזיר. chazir.
Here's what the story has:
so it says when the priests and Aristobulus were besieged, it happened
that the feast called the Passover was come, at which it is
our custom to offer a number of sacrifices to God, but those
that were with Aristobulus wanted sacrifices and desired that their countrymen without
would furnish them with such sacrifices and assured them that they should
have as much money for them as they should desire. But when
they required them to pay a thousand drachmae for each head of
cattle, Aristobulus and the priests willingly undertook to pay for them accordingly,
and then and those with him let down the money over the
wall and gave it to them. Sounds pretty similar other than it's
a קרבן פסח korban Pesach and that he says a thousand drachmae
so part of the point is how much they're demanding. But when
the others had received it they did not deliver the sacrifices, but
arrived at that height of wickedness as to break the assurances they
had given and to be guilty of impiety towards God by not
furnishing those they wanted them with sacrifices. And when the priests found
that they had been cheated and that the agreements they had made
were violated they prayed to God that he would avenge them on
their countrymen. Nor did he delay their punishment, but sent a strong
and vehement storm of wind that destroyed the fruits of the whole
country, so there you go, no עומר Omer. and שתי הלחם, shtei
halechem till a modius of wheat was then bought, whatever that is,
a measure of wheat for 11 drachmae. That's how expensive wheat was.
So there's obviously some very interesting parallels, right, I mean obviously the
money and whatever and destroying the wheat and so on. Of course
there's no pig. So I was wondering, you know, what happened to
the pig, how did, you know, maybe Josephus's version is more accurate
than the גמרא's, Gemara a little closer to the events, what happened
to the pig? And it occurred to me that maybe, you know,
the pig does play a role in the whole story of the
חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, of the Maccabees, because the whole גזירה gezeira of Antiochus
was לא באכול בשר חזיר... lo beechol basar chazir... well, not only
באכול בשר
חזיר.
beechol
basar chazir. No, no, no. גזירת אנטיוכוס gezeirat Antiochus from Maccabees 1
is the king sent letters by messengers to Jerusalem and the towns
of Judah. He directed them to follow the customs strange to the
land, to forbid burnt offerings and sacrifice and drink offerings in the
sanctuary, to profane Sabbath and the festivals, to defile the sanctuary and
the priests, to build altars and sacred precincts and shrines for idols,
to sacrifice swine and other unclean animals and leave their sons uncircumcised.
So the idea of swine, pigs as sacrifices, you know, is sort
of the whole evocative of the whole גזירה gezeira of גזירת אנטיוכוס.
gezeirat Antiochus. So in a way that, you know, really even more
underscores how abominable it is what they're doing. Here they are, you
know, these are the חשמונאים Chashmonaim that have won the war against
Antiochus and in their attempt for power are basically, you know, adopting
the whole modes of Antiochus, basically sending them this pig to sacrifice.
So I wonder, you know, it seems to me that maybe that's
how this story with Josephus got this element of the pig in
it, assuming that that's how it happened. You know, could be חז"ל
Chazal just had a completely different history of it, but Josephus was
closer to the events. So that's one thing in terms of thinking
about the pig and its significance. The other thing I just want
to say and I'll open it for questions and then move on
is, so the idea of Greek wisdom. So, you know, Saul Lieberman
here in his very famous two works, Greek in Jewish Palestine and
Hellenism in Jewish Palestine, so in the beginning one of Hellenism in
Jewish Palestine, his one of his first, his first article is "The
Alleged Ban on Greek Wisdom". And why does he say the alleged
ban? Because he points out and תוספות Tosafot already asked this question,
you know, here the person, anybody who's
מלמד בנו חכמת יוונית. melamed beno chochmat yevanit. You have another... Someone's
going to say, Hey, can I learn חכמת יוונית? chochmat yevanit? And
the answer is, Well, if you've learned כל התורה כולה, kol hatorah
kullah, then you can go learn חכמת יוונית. chochmat yevanit. But it
doesn't sound like there was a prohibition to do it or there
was an ארור. arur. So תוספות Tosafot tries to deal with that.
He says, well, maybe it was an ארור, arur, it wasn't a
strict prohibition. Later it became a prohibition. Anyway, what Saul Lieberman says
is if you look at all the sources, the entire prohibition was
מלמד את בנו חכמת יוונית, melammed et beno chochmat yevanit, to teach
somebody who is still young this, and therefore there was a concern
that it was maybe it would open up the gates of Hellenism
to that person. Whatever this is, obviously it's somehow it was maybe
Greek language, or maybe some sort
of culture and Hellenist, you know, like some way it made Hellenism
accessible. And therefore it was a real threat as בנו beno when
you're young and impressionable. If you're an adult already, then there's no
prohibition. The only issue was the concern about the ביטול תורה. bittul
torah.
Well, his point was not about the ביטול תורה bittul torah of
בנו beno and the מצוות תלמוד תורה. mitzvah talmud torah. His point
was about the threat of Hellenism. Okay, so that's anyway what he
does with that. Okay, some quick questions and then...
My quick question was, it's interesting, they said, you know, as long
as they're עוסק בעבודה osek ba'avodah in some idea. But you know,
because you'd think that it's kind of be both ways and be
neutral. They're doing their עבודה, avodah, but you're helping them. You're giving
them a קרבן. korban And by you, like, giving them a חזיר
chazir of anything, if I were God... that's a
good point. Well, maybe that goes to תוספות'ס Tosafot's point that it
was more about morality than anything else. I mean, notice the גמרא
Gemara doesn't say after it says
it זעזעה ירושלים, zaze'ah yerushalayim, it doesn't say like all of a
sudden they broke into the חומת, chomat, it doesn't tell you what
happened in the next stages to allow them to win. So I
don't know, it's a good question. It goes to why you need
somebody on the inside whispering secrets, you know,
that's all.
Okay, what? Lastly, wonder about this kind of fairy tale quality aspect
of the story of supplying food to your enemies. Right. Contemporary issues
for sure.
supplying aid to Gaza.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Although it's not food here, cause food,
the whole assumption is that they destroyed all the wheat fields and
all they're doing is allowing them to continue the worship. But right,
that's the point.
There you go. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. We're going to have a few more of these stories with
מרדכי. Mordechai. Now.
הנהו שלוש נשים דאייתו שלוש קינין. hanhu shalosh nashim de'ayitu shalosh kinin.
So there were three women that showed up to the בית המקדש
during this time and where מרדכי Mordechai was still around here. And
they brought, all brought with them these קינין kinin which are like
these two birds, you know, as a bird sacrifice. They always come
in pairs of birds. Okay.
חדא אמרה לזיבתי. chada amrah l'zivati. One said, I'm bringing this for
my זיבה, zivah, for my flow.
וחדא אמרה לימתי. v'chada amrah l'yamati. I'm bringing this for my ocean,
which also presumably means a heavy flow.
וחדא אמרה לאונתי. v'chada amrah l'onati. I'm bringing this for my period.
So all of them sounded like they were bringing something relating to
some type of uterine bleeding. Now you don't bring a קרבן korban
for being a נדה, niddah, you bring a קרבן korban, for being
a זבה. zavah. But maybe the assumption was that they were all
having different ways of euphemizing or that they were זבות zavot and
that the period was over and they needed to bring a קרבן,
korban which seems reasonable. סברי מיניה. savri mineih. They assumed זיבתי זבה
ממש, zivati zavah mamash, means she's a זבה. zavah. Right? Or this
person, a woman with a flow not during her normal menstrual period,
but still a uterine flow. לימתי לימתי ממש, liyamati liyamati mamash, literally
my ocean, you know, again, a heavy flow. לאונתי לאונסה. l'onati l'onassa.
וכולו חד חטאת וחד עולה. v'chulu chad chattat v'chad olah. They're all
different ways of describing that they're having a blood flow and therefore
it's a קרבן korban for a זבה. zavah. A זבה zavah woman
brings when the period is over, seven days, clean days, one bird
for a חטאת chattat and one bird for an עולה. olah. אמר
להו מרדכי. amar lehu Mordechai. So מרדכי Mordechai was there and he
said, wait a minute, שמא בזוב סכנה, shema b'zov sakanah, שמא בים
סכנה. shema b'yam sakanah. Maybe it has nothing to do with טומאה.
tumah. Maybe it means that one woman says that because of her
flow, she was, you know, she had a health threat. Maybe it
was a menstrual flow, not a non-menstrual flow, and it's not a
זבה. zavah. So it means that she had a health threat and
she's now recovered and she wants to do it as a... Yeah,
as a... not a תודה, todah, but as an עולה, olah, as
a thanksgiving to God. It has nothing to do with טומאה. tumah.
And the same one בים, b'yam, it may mean she just because
of her flow she was endangered and שמא באונס סכנה. shema b'oness
sakanah. So again, the word ים yam and אונס oness and זוב
zov being explained the same, but it's not to say she's a
זבה, zavah, but to say she had a risky period relating to
flow and now she's better and she's bringing this as an עולה.
olah. שכולו עולות נינהו, shechulu olot ninhu, that they're both עולות. olot.
So not one עולה olah and one חטאת. chattat. בדקו ואשכחו. badku
v'ashkachu. They checked and they found out that he was right, that
that was a good, that that was a good read. היינו דתנן.
hainu detnan. Top of ס"ה ע"א. samech hei amud aleph. That's what
we talk in the משנה. פתחיה על הקינין. Petachyah al hakinin. פתחיה...
Petachyah... excuse me, פתחיה על
הקינין. Petachyah al hakinin. So there was one of the people who
supervised the קינין, kinin, the bird sacrifices. His name was פתחיה. Petachyah.
And we say, who is that? זה... zeh... that he was over,
sort of oversaw the moneys that were given for the bird sacrifices.
And we say, זה מרדכי, zeh Mordechai, that this was מרדכי. Mordechai.
So that connects because now we have
מרדכי Mordechai being involved in this discussion about what the birds were
being brought for. So we're connecting him to this. And the למה
נקרא שמו פתחיה, lama nikra shemo Ptachia, and if it was Mordechai,
why was he called פתחיה? Ptachia? שפותח דברים ודורשן, shepoteach devarim vedorshan,
because as we've seen in the last two stories, he was able
to open up words and interpret them. He was able to figure
out what people were trying to get at and what they were
saying. ויודע בשבעים לשון, veyodeia beshivim lashon, and he happens also to
know all 70 languages. So again, that's I guess what's to be
open, to have accessible, to be able to interpret all different languages.
So the Gemara says one minute, כולו סנהדרין נמי ידעי שבעים לשון.
kulu Sanhedrin nami yadei shivim lashon. What do you mean? What makes
him so special? Don't we say the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin knows all
70 languages? דאמר רבי יוחנן אין מושיבין בסנהדרין אלא בעלי חכמה בעלי
מראה בעלי קומה בעלי זקנה בעלי כשפים. da'amar Rabbi Yochanan ein moshivin
beSanhedrin ela ba'alei chochma ba'alei mareh ba'alei komah ba'alei ziknah ba'alei kshafim.
The only people that get to be on the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, presumably
the סנהדרין הגדול Sanhedrin Hagadol of 71 anyway, are people of wisdom,
of good appearances, of height. So Rashi says some of these is
that they sort of instill a sense of obedience and respect in
the people that they're ruling for. בעלי זקנה, ba'alei ziknah, elderly. בעלי
כשפים, ba'alei kshafim, they know witchcraft. Why is that? So Rashi says
well if you're judging a witch, they don't want the witch to
try to get out of the judgment through or whatever, or the
male witch, the warlock, whatever, through the use of witchcraft, so they
have their own witchcraft to counteract the witchcraft of the witch.
Defense against the dark arts? What? Defense against the dark arts. So
Tosafot says a little bit less whatever,
a little more realistically, that if somebody's testifying or relating to something
as it relates to witchcraft, you'll know what they're talking about, you
know, they're just educated in that so that they can understand what
the testimony is about. ויודעים שבעים לשון, veyodim shivim lashon, and they
know all 70 languages, שלא תהא סנהדרין שומעת מפי התורגמן, shelo tehei
Sanhedrin shoma'at mipi hatorgeman, so you would not need a translator because
the translator can always, you know, twist intentionally or unintentionally what actually
is being said. Now Tosafot by the way suggests, really, everybody knew
all שבעים לשון? shivim lashon? So even if you assume שבעים לשון
shivim lashon is an exaggeration, Tosafot says well maybe you didn't need
everybody to know, maybe it was enough that one or two of
them knew, and one or two of them would hear directly and
him you could trust to report to the rest of the group
what exactly was being said. Nevertheless, the Gemara here is assuming it
means everybody on the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So we're saying what's special with
Mordechai, especially if this assumption is that he's the original Mordechai and
he was on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin anyway? But everybody on the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin had this, so why do you make this big deal? So
the Gemara says אלא, ela, you're right. So that's not what, that
wasn't
his greatness, דהוה בלע לישני ודריש. dehavei balya lishnei vedarish. He would
like mix sort of languages together and be able to interpret them.
והיינו דכתיב מרדכי בלשן, ve'hainu dechtiv Mordechai Balshan, and therefore we have
that Mordechai is also called Balshan in Nechemia and now it does
seem why he is identifying it with the original Mordechai because the
Gemara does identify him with Balshan and it's the time period of
Nechemia is at least more appropriate.
בולל לשון, bolel lashon, mix up the language. Now mix up sounds
like it's the opposite of what we're trying to do, but whatever
it means, it means sort of think creatively about what's being said
in order to understand it. מה? ma? A linguist? Right. Okay, so
again I don't know what to make of the greater significance of
this whole story other than it's interesting, once we talk about Mordechai
to talk about his ability to interpret,
but you know exactly sort of the larger significance, what you do
have obviously is the parallel that here is somebody who's able to
unfold, interpret language, signal appropriately, contrasted to the person who uses Greek
wisdom to do it. And you know, as I said, I think
the larger theme is it's about sort of the use and misuse
of proper and improper methods. So you know, there's nothing bad about
being able to sort of know tricks of communication and understand and
sort of figure out the hidden meaning of what people are saying
if you use it correctly. So Mordechai here is using it to
help bring the right קרבנות, korbanot, to figure out where you bring
the עומר Omer, and the שתי הלחם from, right? The problem is
when you use those things and you use them to communicate to
the people outside and have them send a pig inside. You know,
and the same idea that the very idea of like I was
saying is that the pig also very almost represents someone that's sort
of presenting themselves properly but ultimately it's something, you know, bad and
evil and here you know you're trying to be the king. So
I think it's the question about the mixing up of methods which
may be themselves neutral and not intrinsically bad, but the question is,
you know, how are they being used? So that's what I think
is sort of the larger theme going on here, yes.
So more technically, when you're saying that not all of them needed
to know the 70 languages, so what is this אין מושיבין בסנהדרין
אלא ein moshivin beSanhedrin ela this that the other?
No, Tosafot tries to just be a little more realistic but the
simple read of the Gemara he admits is that they all needed
to know. Okay, so now we go on to the next משנה.
Now that we had that fascinating story about the use of Greek
wisdom, whatever that meant, and about the whole sending up of the
pig, now we go to the next משנה. כיצד היו עושים? keitzad
hayu osim? How would they actually harvest the barley for the עומר?
Omer First, even if it's not שבת, Shabbat. and in a minute
we're going to talk about what if it is שבת. Shabbat Okay,
so what would they do? Right, we sort of left שבת Shabbat.
behind already this last משנה about bringing from nearby was no longer
about שבת.
Shabbat, You never actually answered that, what would they do on שבת,
Shabbos, right? So it was like three people or whatever.
Everybody מחלוקת. machloket. Okay, now what would they do? שלוחי בית דין
יוצאים מערב יום טוב. shluchei beit din yotzim me'erev yom tov. So
שלוחי בית דין shluchei beit din would go out on ערב יום
טוב erev yom tov ועושים אותן כריכות. ve'osim otan kerichot. כריכות מחובר
לקרקע. krichot mechubar lekarka.
They would sort of wrap, you know, a band around some wheat
that was still attached, and they want to make it easy to
cut, you know, afterwards, so they would spend time before יום טוב.
Yontiv. We're going to see that obviously you do the cutting on
the day itself. That was the, that's how what they learn from
the פסוק. pasuk. You do the cutting on the day of the
עומר. Omer. But you don't want to be wasting time that you
don't have to. So you spend time before יום טוב Yontiv identifying
where's the grain you want to cut, you wrap it together in
a way that it's a סימן, siman, and then afterwards you're going
to go out right on, right on the, you know, day after
יום טוב, Yontiv, the day of the עומר, Omer and you'll go
right there and you'll cut it immediately. You know, for some people
that's why the idea of making a little mark in the חלה
challah before you make המוציא Hamotzi is like so that after you
make the ברכה, bracha, you're not trying to decide where should I
cut from and there's a הפסק, hefsek, you have the mark, you
start the mark. Of course, as we know what happens is you
make the ברכה bracha and you say, 'now where's that mark that
I put in?' so it doesn't really help. But what?
Then you end up tearing it. Anyway, okay, so that they would,
they would do that beforehand while it was still attached. כדי שיהא
נוח לקצור, kedei she-yehei noach liktzor, it would be easy to cut
out when it came the time, the day after יום טוב. Yontiv.
כל העיירות הסמוכות לשם מתכנסות לשם, kol ha-ayarot ha-smuchot l'sham mitkansot l'sham,
all the villages nearby that field would gather around in that field,
כדי שיהא נקצר בעסק גדול, kedei she-yeikatzar b'esek gadol, in that it
should be cut in a big hubbub, big to-do, a
big to-do.
Okay, now why? We'll see in a minute that the whole idea
was to publicize which is the day that they're cutting the עומר
Omer and starting the counting from, in order to also publicize which
is the day that's going to be שבועות Shavuos is 50 days
hence, and because that was all debated between them and the other
sectarians, you know, about when do, what is ממחרת השבת. mi-macharas ha-Shabbos.
So they made a point of making a very big to-do about
it that it was publicized. And it was, as I'm saying, it's
not only publicized, but as we're about to see in this description,
that it was a, that it was like a consensus. No, a
consensus. They're going to shape it as if everybody here, it's, it's
universally known and everybody knows we do it this way and so
on, to sort of frame the other opinion
as the, as, you know, marginal and, and, you know, a trivial
opinion. So they're framing this as the consensus. Okay, so let's take
a look. Okay, כיוון
שחשכה. keivan she-chashcha.
Now it's got became nightfall. The point is like this: it's now
16th of ניסן. Nisan. If you wait till the morning, the morning
is when you bring the עומר. Omer, You want the עומר Omer
ready to be brought first thing in the morning, so you cut
it the night before, which is halachically the same day. So we
understand that the cutting has to be on the day of bringing,
but not daytime; you cut it the night before the day of
bringing, which is halachically the day, so you can bring it on
that day.
How do they see?
They took, they took flash... yeah, they exactly, they took torches. כיוון
שחשכה אמר להן. keivan she-chashcha amar lahen. So he said to the
villagers, whoever was in charge, what? בא השמש? ba ha-shemesh? Oh, yeah,
he said to the villagers all around, אמר להן, amar lahen, 'בא
השמש? ba ha-shemesh? Has the sun set?' אומר, omer, they all said
'הן, hen, yes.' 'בא השמש? ba ha-shemesh? Has the sun set?' אומר,
omer, 'הן', hen they all said yes. 'מגל זו? magal zu? Should
I use this scythe?' אומר, omer, 'הן', hen they said yes. 'מגל
זו? magal zu? Should I use this?' אומר, omer, 'הן', hen they
said yes. 'קופה זו? kuppa zu? Should I use this basket?' אומר,
omer, 'הן', hen yes. 'קופה זו? kuppa zu? Yes, should I use
this basket?' אומר, omer, 'הן', hen they said yes. Now, if it
happened to be בשבת, be-Shabbos, if they were doing it on שבת,
Shabbos. אומר, omer, 'שבת זו? Shabbos zu? Should I do it even
today? It's שבת.' Shabbos אומר, omer, 'הן', hen they said yes. 'שבת
זו? Shabbos zu? On this שבת Shabbat, I should cut?' אומר, omer,
'הן', hen they said yes. 'אקצור? ektzor? Now it's okay, I'm all
ready, should I now start cutting?' והם אומרים לו 'קצור'. ve-hem omrim
lo katzor 'קצור', katzor I cut. 'אקצור? ektzor? Should I cut?' והם
אומרים לו 'קצור'. ve-hem omrim lo katzor שלוש פעמים על כל דבר
ודבר. shalosh pe'amim al kol davar ve-davar. Three times they did this
whole cycle. Not clear because each thing he says twice, I know.
He did each twice, three times, so was it asking six times?
Or was it... okay. Anyway, either way. והם אומרים לו 'הן הן
הן'. ve-hem omrim lo hen hen hen Yes, yes, yes. Why? כל
כך למה? kol kach lama? Why? מפני הבייתוסין, mipnei ha-Baitusin, because of
the בייתוסין. Baitusin. We don't hear of them too much, normally we
hear about the צדוקין, Tzedukim, but here it's identified with בייתוסין. Baitusin.
שהיו אומרים 'אין קצירת העומר במוצאי יום טוב'. she-hayu omrim ein katzirat
ha-omer be-motzaei yom tov You don't do it on the 16th, you
do it on ממחרת השבת, mi-macharas ha-Shabbos, on a
Sunday. And therefore they made a big thing and, and then I'm
saying it's not just a big like proclamation, 'hey, we're doing it,'
but it's, it's done in a way that like he's asking and
everybody agrees. You know, it's the consensus. Every, you know, any normal
person knows that you do it today, it's only you crazies that
you have a different idea. Okay, I think it's really done specifically
to shape it as a consensus. Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now
we taught. And this is not exactly a תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan,
it's a quote from מסכת תענית. masechet ta'anit.
מגילת תענית, Megillat Ta'anit, I should say. מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit is
a, is a, you know, is an ancient book written in the
בית שני bayis sheni period, which lists the days that you don't,
you're not allowed to fast on, the minor holidays because of a
lot of like minor events that happened at the time that were
historically were significant, don't have big lasting historical significance, but they were
recorded there as days not to fast on and some days that
were particularly important not even to eulogize on. By the way, that's
where we get the story of חנוכה, Chanukah, because it's recorded there
in מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit that those are eight days that you
do not fast on or eulogize on. So here's what we have
from
מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. אלו יומייא דלא להתענאה בהון, eilu yomaya d'la
l'is'ana'a behon, the following days you don't fast on, ומקצתהון דלא למספד
בהון, u-miktzahon d'la l'mispas behon, and some of them are so weighty
that you don't eulogize on. מריש ירחא דניסן עד תמניא ביה, me-reish
yarcha de-Nisan ad tamanya bei, from ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nisan
until the eighth, איתוקם תמידא, itokam tamida, the bringing of the... bringing
of the תמיד Tamid was established. We'll see what that means, there
was a whole debate and it was established the way the תמיד
Tamid was brought and that was a holiday, דלא למספד, de'lo l'mispad,
that you would not and it's so important you don't even eulogize.
ומיתמניא ביה ועד סוף מועדא, u'mitamnaya beh ve'ad sof moada, from the
eighth of ניסן Nissan until the end of the מועד, moed, of
the end of פסח, Pesach, איתוסף חגא דשבועייא, itosaf chaga d'shavuaya, it
was established the holiday of שבועות, Shavuot, the Pharisees won their debate
with the ביתוסין Baitusin and it was established that you know, sort
of in practice, they sort of you know, they minimized the opposition
that שבועות Shavuot you start bringing from the עומר on the sixteenth
of ניסן. Nissan. Where are we?
דלא למספ... de'lo l'misp... okay, דלא למספד, de'lo l'mispad, that you would
not eulogize. Now if you look at the side, the גרסא girsa
is not דלא למספד, de'lo l'mispad, but דלא להתענא. de'lo l'itana. It
was not as big of a victory and rather than saying not
to eulogize, they only said, and רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both
have this גרסא girsa here as well, a whole question of different
גמרות, Gemaras, anyway, not to fast. So one thing we'll talk about
later is which was the greater victory and why, but for now
we'll pause on that. Let's take a look at the debate itself.
מריש ירחא דניסן ועד תמניא ביה, M'resh yarcha d'Nissan ve'ad tamnaya beh,
from ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan until the
eighth, איתוקם תמידא דלא למספד, itokam tamida d'lo l'mispad, the תמיד Tamid
was established and therefore you do not have eulogized. What was the
issue with the תמיד? Tamid? שהיו הצדוקים אומרים, she'hayu ha'Tzedukim omrim, the
Sadducees would say, יחיד מתנדב ומביא תמיד, yachid mitnadeiv u'meivi tamid, an
individual can donate and bring the תמיד. Tamid. מאי דרש, mai darash,
where do they get this from? את הכבש האחד תעשה בבוקר, et
ha'keves ha'echad ta'aseh va'boker, you in the singular shall bring the one
lamb in the morning, ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערבים. ve'et ha'keves
ha'sheni ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim. So therefore an individual can bring. Now what
does it mean? Why isn't it just considered an עולה? olah? But
maybe it means that I'm going to say today I am going
to dedicate the תמיד Tamid with my money. Today's תמיד Tamid has
been sponsored by so-and-so. Okay, so that's what the צדוקים Tzedukim said.
Okay, where are we? תעשה בין הערבים. ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim. מה אשיבו
ליה, ma ashivu leh, what did they respond, how did they disprove
it? Because it says את קרבני לחמי לאשי תשמרו, et korbani lachmi
l'ishai tishm'ru, you collectively shall observe
my
offerings, תשמרו tishm'ru which all have to come from communal funds.
That's such a good answer!
I know, so yeah, that was it. That's all they could say
back. And the other thing is, besides which sometimes singular means you
as a collective. Right?
No, or it means you can just make sure that it's brought,
forget about who sponsors.
Anyway, somehow that was seen that they won that debate. But again,
I also think it's interesting, and this is just my speculation, is
that there's a little subtext that notice it's the צדוקים Tzedukim that
are trying to break away from the communal reality. Right? You know,
they're trying to say an individual can sort of impose his will
and identity, you know, have it be his קרבן korban. and not
the communal קרבן. korban And sort of I think the whole idea
that there's, you know, the way חזל Chazal are framing it, right?
Who's a sectarian is always depending who you're asking. You know, history's
written by the winners. Right? So the way חזל Chazal are framing
it, you know, they are Judaism and everybody else is a sectarian.
So you know, so therefore they're saying the same way by the
עומר, that was the consensus and it's crazy people that had a
different version. So here too, you know, it's the צדוקים, Tzedukim, they
want to do something, they want to take it away from the
communal reality, from the consensus. They want it to be like an
individual קרבן korban. and not a communal קרבן. Anyway, that's just my
little subtext read, which you can take it or leave it.
Why did it take them eight days to respond? Why...
It was a debate that went on for eight days and somehow
in the end, I don't know, nobody knows. Obviously a lot of
this has a lot less to do with the substance of the
argument and probably a lot more to do with various other types
of political and other, you know, factors in terms of who wins
these debates.
Because it doesn't seem like a convincing retort.
Right?
For eight days you'd think like one day you'd establish.
No, yeah, it was somehow some type of a debate that lasted
eight days.
Okay, so now it goes on, it says like this. That was
that one. Now, now we get to
שבועות. Shavuos. Okay, ומיתמניא ביה ועד סוף מועדא, u'mitamnaya beh ve'ad sof
moada, from the eighth of ניסן Nissan until the end of פסח
Pesach they were debating
שבועות. Shavuot. איתוסף חגא דשבועייא, itosaf chaga d'shavuaya, they established the holiday
of שבועות. Shavuot. דלא למספד, de'lo l'mispad, and therefore we don't eulogize
or we don't fast during those that period of time. Why was
that? שהיו ביתוסין אומרים, she'hayu Baitusin omrim, the ביתוסין Baitusin were saying,
עצרת אחר השבת, atzeret achar ha'Shabbat, that שבועות Shavuos falls out on
a Sunday because you start the עומר on a Sunday, presumably the
first שבת, shabbat. the Sunday presumably
after the first day of פסח. Pesach. Okay. נטפל להם רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי. nitpal lahem Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was sort of assigned to them. But again,
נטפל להם nitpal lahem from the word טפל tafel means sort of
was trivial, and the whole point, that verb already signals that he's
not treating them seriously. Like he's just humoring them. Okay. נטפל להם
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. nitpal lahem Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai.
It's sort of like, you know, pretended to like, you know, tag
along to them?
No. No, let's take a look. ואמר להם, ve'amar lahem, and he
said to them, שוטים, shotim, idiots. That's a good way to start
a conversation. Idiots! מנין לכם, minayin lachem, where do you think... where
do you get this idea from that you start on Sunday? I
don't know, the פסוק pasuk says ממחרת השבת. mi'mochorat ha'Shabbat. Okay, but
somehow he already starts by casting their position as completely absurd. Where
do you get this crazy idea? Okay. ולא היה אדם אחד שהיה
משיבו, ve'lo hayah adam echad she'hayah meshivo, no, there was not
one man who was answering him.
Again, probably not because they didn't have a good פסוק pasuk that
said ממחרת השבת, mimacharat hashabbat, but if, you know, the people in
charge are sort of saying, idiots, where do you get this from,
who's willing, who wants to get into that type of a debate?
Right, the deck is a little loaded. Okay. חוץ מזקן אחד, chutz
mizaken echad, here again is,
there's an elder, there's an elder again, שהיה מפטפט כנגדו. shehayah mipatpeit
kenegdo. He was like sputtering, not sputtering, you know, whatever, he was
like, what would be the word? Not stuttering but like, you know,
like chattering or whatever. You know, again, it's not a positive word.
It's sort of saying, you know, he's sputtering, sputtering maybe would be
the idea. Okay, opposite. He was willing to go
up against רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי.
Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai. What? Blabbering? Yeah, okay. Yeah, I think maybe a little
more like sputtering, like he was just saying silly things. Like, okay,
anyway, he was willing to take his position. And look at his
position, where he doesn't even quote the פסוק pasuk from the שבת.
Shabbat משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, I know, it's an unfair, the deck's
a stack. ואמר משה רבינו אוהב ישראל היה. ve'amar Moshe Rabbeinu ohev
yisrael hayah. What? It happened. Right. As long as you're on the
winner's side. Okay. משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu loved the Jewish people. ויודע
שעצרת יום אחד הוא. veyodeia she'atzeret yom echad hu. He knew that
שבועות Shavuot was only one day, נעבעך, nebach, a holiday, it's only
one day. You know, anybody who's lived in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz
will tell you how important it is to at least have two
days of every יום טוב. yom tov. So therefore, עמד ותקנה אחר
שבת, amad vatiknah achar shabbat, so he made sure that שבועות Shavuot
would fall out on a Sunday, כדי שישראל מתענגין שני ימים, kedei
sheyisrael mitangrin shnei yamim, so at least they could have two days
to celebrate שבועות. Shavuot. קרא לו מקרא זה, kara lo mikra zeh,
so רב יוחנן בן זכאי Rav Yochanan ben Zakkai responded, he quoted
the following פסוק, pasuk, אחד עשר יום מחורב דרך הר שעיר. achad
asar yom meChorev derech har Se'ir. It says that, you know, the
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was eleven days from הר סיני. Har Sinai.
ואם משה רבינו אוהב ישראל היה, ve'im Moshe Rabbeinu ohev yisrael hayah,
according to you that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu loved the Jewish people,
which of course everybody assumes that he loved the Jewish people, but
according to you that he's willing to do anything in order
to for the sake of the Jewish people, למה עיכבם במדבר ארבעים
שנה? lamah ikcham bamidbar arbaim shana? Why did he make them wander
for forty years, it's eleven days to get to ארץ ישראל? Eretz
Yisrael? Obviously, משה Moshe didn't care about the Jewish people and your
whole proof was a stupid proof and it was a stupid answer.
Okay, fine. אמר לו, amar lo, so he said to him, רבי
בכך אתה פוטרני? rabbi bekach at potrani? That's how you are dismissing
me? With that type of response? At least give me a serious
response. אמר לו, amar lo, he said back to him, שוטה, shoteh,
idiot again. Good way to frame the debate. ולא תהא תורה שלימה
שלנו כשיחה בטילה שלכם. ve-lo tehei torah shleimah shelanu kesichah beteilah shelachem.
Our pure, complete
תורה Torah is not equateable with your stupid speech. So we can't
have a discussion. We have the truth, you have your idiotic ideas.
You know, I'm not even going to bother to deign it with
a response.
Okay. You are very deeply offended, right.
Well,
aren't they fellow Jews?
No,
they have important religious points to be making and they look, part
of the problem here is that the פסוקים psukim read quite nicely
as like to say literally on Sunday, right? פשט pshat of the
פסוק. pasuk. So maybe the only way that if you believe in
your tradition, but you know that they have a pretty strong argument
on the opposite way, you have to maybe skew the debate in
order that you can sort of, you know, win, be persuasive. You
know, so that's, I mean it's not pleasant, but that sort of
seems to be what's going on, which gets to the question of
which was the greater holiday. רש״י Rashi says ironically that the reason
שבועות Shavuot was the winning of this battle of שבועות Shavuot was
less significant, according to this גירסא girsah you don't fast but you
are allowed to eulogize is because he says, well, that was such
an easy battle to win. I mean, come on, there's so many
פסוקים psukim that we're going to bring in a minute to prove
how we know שבועות Shavuot is
the sixteenth of ניסן. Nisan. Of course, you could have said the
exact opposite, which is sort of what תוספות Tosafot says, which is
it wasn't such an easy battle to win and the victory wasn't
so conclusive. So therefore, we're not going to make it such a
huge victory the same way we made the other thing a huge
victory. So you know, there's a whole question here, was this scene
of a bigger victory, an easier victory, or less conclusive victory? And
we're now going to spend the remainder of the דף trying to
prove what רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai is taking
as being so patently obvious. It's not so patently obvious, and we're
going to try to use the remainder of the דף to try
to prove it. Right, did you want to say something before we
go on?
Obviously, but
when we use this kind of language to some of us
silent the debate,
yes, so
not nice.
Bullying, that's a good word.
Is there any comment about that or is that just considered like
an appropriate way?
No, it's hard to find people that are sympathizing with בייתוסי Baitusi
in the rabbinic literature.
Nobody's discussed no, nobody
says like well, maybe you're right but why use that language? No.
But again, what I think it really is reflective of is that,
you know, it's like the guy the famous joke they say, somebody
gave a speech, they walked up to the podium afterwards, they found
his note card and written in one of the margins was, argument
weak, speak quickly.
So if you like, so it's like argument weak, speak harshly. So
okay, you don't have, you know, in the end, you might not
be able to win on substance so you've got to... little bit
silence the opposition.
So your interpretation.
That's my read of this, right, being the standard. I'm right, correct.
Everybody, I mean again, רש"י Rashi says they didn't make such a
הלכה halacha of it because it was such an easy win, which
is so bizarre, okay, תוספות Tosafot disagrees with that. Okay, so let's
tee a little bit now in the גמרא Gemara really tries to
prove it.
You know, there was a rabbi in the community that I used
to go to frequently that I quickly learned that whenever he said
now listen carefully in one of his שיעורים, shiurim, that's when he
was going to make a ridiculous point,
a theological point, and he said listen carefully so you would think
oh I didn't listen carefully, that's why it
didn't make sense.
There you go. It sounds like I don't know what the גמרא
Gemara, is going to conclude here, but my guess is that the
argument actually could probably be won on a textual basis or whatever
you want to call it by the צדוקים. Tzedukim.
Right,
so that's what I was saying. That's what you were saying. Yeah,
that in terms of the substance of the argument, it's hard to
win in terms of right, though
the modern day implications are quite striking.
For why? We still go against the idea of going by תורה
שבעל
פה,
Torah
she'be'al
peh, going by the מסורה. masora. No, I mean, you don't engage
with the theological arguments or arguments of הלכה halacha with reform, God
forbid.
Oh, I see.
Oh, if you think that they have more of a convincing argument,
even though you know that from your perspective what they're saying is
wrong, you don't want to lose,
we also מסתמך mistamech the answer is this is the מסורה, masora,
it's not this way or that way on the
פסוק. pasuk.
Right. Well why doesn't he say that then?
Well, that's not going to win. I mean, because the whole point
is they're debating what the מסורה masora is, debating
what בייתוסים Baitosim don't buy into that מסורה. masora. Okay, so let's
take on... so let's go take a look.
Okay, כתוב אחד אומר Katuv echad omer so now here we're going
to start actually proving it. כתוב אחד אומר, Katuv echad omer, one
פסוק pasuk says, תספרו חמישים יום, Tisperu chamishim yom, count fifty days,
וכתוב אחד אומר, vekatuv echad omer, and one פסוק pasuk says,
שבע שבתות תמימות תהיינה, Sheva shabbatot temimot tihyena, seven full weeks, הכיצד,
Hakeitzad, how do you satisfy both פסוקים? pesukim? So, כאן ביום טוב
שחל להיות בשבת כאן ביום טוב שחל להיות באמצע שבת, Kan beyom
tov shechal lihyot beshabbat kan beyom tov shechal lihyot be'emtza shabbat, whether
the יום טוב yom tov falls out on שבת Shabbat or during
the week. Why? Because שבע שבתות תמימות, sheva shabbatot temimot, full weeks,
the גמרא Gemara, understands means a week that starts on Sunday. So
one פסוק pasuk says you can get full weeks, how can you
get full weeks? If יום טוב yom tov falls out on שבת
Shabbat then you start the counting on Sunday, which makes the בייתוסים
Baitosim happy. But it says it's not always going to be full
weeks. Sometimes you're just going to have a count of days and
not a count of full weeks and that'll be when יום טוב
yom tov falls out on any other day of the week and
you're going to start not on a Sunday but on a different
day.
It only says 49 days, so why does it say 50?
Well we're not dealing with the 50. Oh, well okay, that's a
good question.
It's because of ממחרת השבת.
Mimochorat haShabbat.
Right, because it's not really שבת Shabbat all the time.
Right, well that's the point, if שבת Shabbat means יום טוב, yom
tov, it's not always going to be full weeks, and therefore the
idea of full weeks is off, so תוספות Tosafot deals with the
problem, surprisingly not in the גמרא, why it says 50 days if
it's only 49 days. Okay, תוספות basically has two answers and there's
a רא"ש that has a third. תוספות'ס Tosafot's answer is basically one
is 50 days means until the 50th day, and then on the
50th, עד ולא עד בכלל. Ad velo ad bichlal. Okay, or another
answer which is more or less the same is עד ממחרת השבת
השביעית תספרו חמישים יום והקרבתם מנחה חדשה להשם. Ad mimochorat hashabbat hashvi'it
tisperu chamishim yom vehikravtem mincha chadasha l'Hashem. Day 50 is שבועות, Shavuot,
but not תספרו חמישים יום. tisperu chamishim yom. The רא"ש says, amazingly,
that the תורה's Torah rounding, the same way when the תורה Torah
says 40 lashes חז"ל Chazal interprets it to mean 39, it says
50, it really means 49. But it's interesting that the whole point
that the תורה Torah said 50 and we keep 49 days is
not discussed in the גמרא, it's discussed by the ראשונים. Rishonim. Yes.
Just a total side question. What? Could this be maybe very beginning
of Christianity that there had to be some more power struggle civilization?
Maybe, but the sectarianism began well before Christianity. Christianity itself started as
a Jewish sect, so I would not put it necessarily in that
context.
Okay, well let me just read one more line. Okay, so let's
just read one more line. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אינו
צריך, eino tzarich, you don't need to learn it from there, I'll
learn it from another פסוק. pasuk. אינו צריך, Eino tzarich, הרי הוא
אומר, harei hu omer, the verse says תספר לך, tispar lach, count
for you. So again, different than what we said before that the
singular language means the individual, here we're saying what חז"ל's Chazal more
general approach is that the singular language refers to כלל ישראל Klal
Yisrael as a corporate entity. So therefore it says you shall count
תספר לך, tispar lach, so it means you the singular entity should
count. Now how does that happen? So it says not as individuals.
ספירה תלויה בבית דין, Sefira tluya b'veit din, so it's dependent on
the בית דין beit din שהן יודעין לחדש ממחרת השבת ממחרת יום
טוב. she'hein yodein l'chadesh mimochorat hashabbat mimochorat yom tov.
They know when the day after שבת Shabbat is because it's the
day after יום טוב. yom tov. יצתה שבת בראשית, Yatzta Shabbat bereishit,
which excludes the normal שבת שספירה בכל אדם shesefira bechol adam
that every individual does it. So what's he saying? He's saying like
this, since in one place, normally it says וספרתם לכם, usfartem lachem,
which actually from which we learn that it's not a counting done
by בית דין, beit din, it's a counting that each individual does,
the use of the plural means each and every individual. But in
one of the places it says תספר לך. tispar lach. Singular, so
somehow this counting is dependent on something that is done by כלל
ישראל *Klal Yisrael*. Now what's done by כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael* or
בית דין *Beis Din* representing כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael*? Making שבת *Shabbos*
isn't done by כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael*, determining which day שבת *Shabbos*
is, that happens naturally. But if the counting takes place in reference
to פסח *Pesach* and that's in reference to when the new month
was established, then that's a counting that is dependent on the act
of כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael* and on the act of בית דין
*Beis Din* to determine when the months are. So because of the
use of the singular, he says it's dependent on when the months
are established, and therefore we know it's dependent on פסח *Pesach* and
not dependent on שבת *Shabbos*. So we will continue tomorrow, more proofs
of this obvious point, that פסח *Pesach* שבועות *Shavuos* starts and the
עומר *Omer* begins the day after יום טוב *Yom Tov* and not
the day after שבת *Shabbos*. Thank you.